Guide to the David Olson Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
David Olson papers
1915-2008
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
5672
Olson, David J.,$d1941-2012
9.05 cubic feet 10 boxes and 1 oversized file
University of Washington professor of political science, founding chair of the Harry Bridges Center for Labor Studies
University of Washington professor of political science, founding chair of the Harry Bridges Center for Labor Studies, scholar on urban and labor politics.
David Olson (Ph.D., University of Wisconsin) was Professor Emeritus of Political Science and the Harry Bridges Endowed Chair Emeritus in Labor Studies. He researched state, urban and labor politics in the United States. He was the co-author or co-editor of Black Politics: The Inevitability of Conflict (Holt, Rinehart and Winston) Theft of the City: Readings in Corruption in Urban America (Indiana), Commission Politics: The Processing of Racial Crisis in America (Trans-Action Books), Governing the United States (McGraw Hill), and To Keep The Republic (McGraw Hill). He also published numerous articles on urban politics, state politics, political violence, seaport politics, congestion pricing, living wage campaigns, term limits, and labor politics. In 2005 he received the S. Sterling Munro Public Service Teaching Award and in 2007 was named the inaugural Distinguished Civic Educator Award by the Washington State Senate. In 2006 Olson was knighted by the King of Norway as knight of the first class, order of merit for contributions to US/Norway scholarly exchange relations.
Outside the University, Olson advised or served as a consultant to various state, county, and municipal governments as well as community groups and the Ford Foundation on subjects ranging from evacuation under radiological emergency, to seaport organization, to publicly owned railroads, to political primary systems, to transportation organization, to trade union contract disputes.
David Olson died on Sept. 15, 2012.
Organized into 2 accessions.
Accession No. 5672-001, David Olson Papers, 1915-2008
Accession No. 5672-002, David Olson papers, 1937-2006
Materials relating to the founding of the Harry Bridges Chair of Labor Studies at the University of Washington, research in labor, labor unions and urban politics, the Washington State blanket primary and role as an expert witness in primary election systems.
No restrictions on access.
David J. Olson, 10/26/2011
A separate collection of David Olson's papers are held by the Wisconsin Historical Society as part of the
Michael Lipsky and David J. Olson Papers
Olson, David J.,$d1941-2012$vArchives; Blue Moon Tavern Preservation Society$xHistory$vArchives; Harry Bridges Center for Labor Studies (University of Washington); Harry Bridges Center for Labor Studies (University of Washington)$xHistory$vArchives; International Longshore and Warehouse Union$xHistory$vArchives; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union$xHistory$vArchives; International Longshoremen's Association$xHistory$vArchives; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Port of Seattle$xHistory$vArchives; University of Washington.$bCenter for Labor Studies$xHistory$vArchives; University of Washington.$bDepartment of Political Science$xHistory$vArchives; University of Washington.$bUniversity Archives; Washington Dental Service$xHistory$vArchives; Business correspondence; Contracts; Ephemera; Newspaper clippings; Personal correspondence; Photographs; Press releases; Records (Documents); Research (documents); Slides (photographs); Speeches; Historians$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives; Labor movement$zUnited States$xHistory$vArchives; Labor unions$zUnited States$xHistory$vArchives; Political scientists$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives; Primaries$xHistory$vArchives; Strikes and lockouts$xStevedores$xHistory$vArchives; University Archives/Faculty Papers; Labor History; Washington (State)
- David Olson Papers, 1915-2008; 1969-2008; 5672-001; 6.48 cubic feet 7 boxes plus one oversized file
  Materials relating to the founding of the Harry Bridges Chair of Labor Studies at the University of Washington, Olson's research in labor and urban politics, and his role as an expert witness in primary election systems. Three large format photographs documenting longshore techology, containerization, and the development of the Port of Seattle. One box of slides.
  The collection is arranged into 2 series:
  SERIES 1: DAVID OLSON PERSONAL PAPERS
  SERIES 2: DAVID OLSON PROFESSIONAL PAPERS
  Series 1 includes all of David Olson's personal papers, such as pictures and projects he worked on outside of his professional career. Series 2 includes all of David Olson's professional papers, such as press clippings, his political science teaching career, labor research and the founding of the Harry Bridges Chair, as well as his role as an expert witness in several trial cases. The second series is also further subdivided into subseries and parts to establish the different categories of David Olson's professional career.
  Open to all users
  Bibliographic Source: David J. Olson
  - DAVID OLSON PERSONAL PAPERS, SERIES 1
    - Personal Pictures, Subseries A
      - Personal Pictures, circa 1990s (Box-folder 1/1)
      - 3 photographs of Port of Seattle, undated (Folder:oversize 8)
    - Blue Moon Tavern Preservation Society, Subseries B
      - Blue Moon Tavern Preservation Society [Part I], 1989 (Box-folder 1/2)
      - Blue Moon Tavern Preservation Society [Part II], 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - DAVID OLSON PROFESSIONAL PAPERS, SERIES 2
    - Publications by David Olson; Press Clippings about David Olson, Subseries A
      - Publications about/by David Olson, 1987-2005 (Box-folder 1/4-1/11)
      - Publications about/by David Olson, 1990-2005 (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Publications about/by David Olson, 1998-2003 (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Publications about/by David Olson, 2000 (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Publications about/by David Olson, 1981-2008 (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Publications about/by David Olson, 1981-2003 (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Publications by/about Olson [The Future of the Public Port Authority Privatized, Federalized, or Status Quo; California Ports; Governance of US Public Ports; Economic Development and the Role of Public Enterprise; Public Port Accountability], 1968-1998 (Box-folder 1/10)
      - David Olson's presentations, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Service with a Smile Project: The First 50 Years of Washington Dental Service, Subseries B
      - Service with a Smile [The First 50 Years of Washington Dental Service], 2003-2004 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Harry Bridges Center for Labor Studies, Subseries C
      - Correspondence about the Harry Bridges Center for Labor Studies, Part 1
        - Robert D. Duggan Correspondence, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 1/13)
        - Correspondence - The Harry Bridges Chair, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Correspondence with Chuck Bergquist On Bridges Center, Part 2
        - Chuck Bergquist Correspondence, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 1/15)
      - The Harry Bridges Center, Part 3
        - Bridges Bust issue, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 1/16)
        - History Early years of The Harry Bridges Chair, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 1/17)
        - The Harry Bridges Chair, 1990-1997 (Box-folder 2/1)
        - Noriko Sawada Bridges: "To Be Or Not To Be (There's No Such Option)" [Poem about being interned as a Japanese American], c. 1990 (Box-folder 2/2)
        - Popular Norwegian Poems [Gus Rystad], 1974-1999 (Box-folder 2/3)
        - Center for Labor Studies, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Conference on Harry Bridges, Part 4
        - Miscellaneous Photos, Video Recordings [Bridges Conference and Bust Dedication], 1994 (Box-folder 2/8)
        - Conference on Harry Bridges [Part I], 1991-1994 (Box-folder 2/5)
        - Conference on Harry Bridges [Part II], 1992-1994 (Box-folder 2/6)
        - Press Clippings of Bridges Chair Dedication, 1992 (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Building Bridges Newsletter, Part 5
        - Building Bridges Newsletter of the Center for Labor Studies, 1995-2005 (Box-folder 2/9)
        - The Harry Bridges Chair [Building Bridges Newsletters, The ILWU Story], 1961-2008 (Box-folder 2/10)
      - David Olson as Harry Bridges Chair, Part 6
        - David Olson (invitations), 1990-1995 (Box-folder 2/11)
        - David Olson (pictures), Undated (Box-folder 2/12)
        - Harry Bridges Chair in Labor Studies, 1992-2005 (Box-folder 2/13)
        - Letters on David Olson Appointment to Bridges Chair, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/14)
        - David Olson: New Harry Bridges Chair, 1994-2007 (Box-folder 2/15)
        - David Olson: Achievements [Part I], 1992-2005 (Box-folder 2/16)
        - David Olson: Achievements [Part II], 1992-2006 (Box-folder 2/17)
      - Labor Studies Scholarships, Part 7
        - Labor Studies Scholarships [Gundlach Scholarship, Martin and Anne Jugum Scholarship, Building Bridges Newsletters], 1994-2000 (Box-folder 2/18)
        - Martin Jugum, 1995-2000 (Box-folder 2/19)
      - Committees: Standing/Visiting for Center for Labor Studies, Part 8
        - Visiting Committee - Center for Labor Studies, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 2/20)
        - Standing Committee - Center for Labor Studies, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 2/21)
      - Working Paper and Publication of Bridges Center, Part 9
        - Working Papers for Labor Studies [Faue, Elizabeth. 1993. "Outfoxing the frost" gender, community-based organization, and the contemporary American labor movement. Seattle, Wash: Center for Labor Studies, University of Washington.], 1993-1994 (Box-folder 2/22)
    - Political Science Career, Subseries D
      - Teaching Assistant Issues: Joel Allen Case and UW Teaching Assistants Strike, Part 1
        - University of Washington TA Organizing and Strike, 2000 (Box-folder 3/1)
        - The Joel Allen Case, Indiana, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - Thank You Letters, Part 2
        - David Olson: Thank You Letters [Part I], 1978-2005 (Box-folder 3/3)
        - David Olson: Thank You Letters [Part II], 1970-2001 (Box-folder 3/4)
      - Involvement with Different Universities: Reviews of Political Science Departments, Guest Lectures, Sabbaticals, Position Offers, Part 3
        - David Olson: Involvement with Different Universities, 1971-2010 (Box-folder 3/5)
        - Professorship Positions and Offers from Universities [Outside Offers], 1967-1987 (Box-folder 3/6)
        - Sabbatical Leave [Course Syllabi, Exams], 1972-2003 (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Professorship at the University of Washington, Part 4
        - Faculty Legislative Representative, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 3/8)
        - David Olson Joins UW Faculty, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 3/9)
        - Graduate Program Revision Committee [Final Reports], 1978 (Box-folder 3/10)
        - Professor and Transcripts: Series of Interviews for Academic Year 1983-1984 (Box-folder 3/11)
        - Political Science Courses [382 Course Syllabi and Guest Lecturers], 2001-2006 (Box-folder 3/12)
        - Political Science Department in the 1960s [News Articles, In the 1960s the UW Political Science Department was deeply divided. This file, cultivated by Prof. Charles Cassinelli and presented to me, charts the wores of the department], 1963-2000 (Box-folder 3/13)
        - Nominations, 1973-1990 (Box-folder 3/14)
      - Chair of the Political Science Department, Part 5
        - Donald R Matthews: Political Science Chair, 1984-2007 (Box-folder 3/15)
        - Leaving the Chairmanship [Department of Political Science at the University of Washington], 1987-1989 (Box-folder 3/16)
      - Correspondence with Indiana University, Part 6
        - Correspondence, Indiana University (part 1 of 2), 1969-1976 (Box-folder 3/17)
        - Correspondence, Indiana University (part 2 of 2), 1969-1976 (Box-folder 3/18)
      - Consultations on Various Projects, Part 7
        - Puget Sound Pilots, Undated (Box-folder 3/19)
        - Exchange with Edward C. Banfield, 1971 (Box-folder 3/20)
        - Expert Witness Deposition on Long Island Lighting Company, 1983 (Box-folder 3/21)
        - Boise State University Review, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 3/22)
        - Contract between David Olson and Little, Brown and Company (Inc). [Correspondence About Not Publishing " Banfield Authors" Collection of Essays Responding to The Unheavenly City], 1962-1974 (Box-folder 3/23)
        - Dissertation UW: The Political Response to Race Riots in Three American Cities, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3/24)
        - Washington State Transportation Commission [David Olson Agrees to Provide Facilitation Services in Support of the WSTC Retreat], 2005-2007 (Box-folder 3/25)
        - Alaska Railroad Transfer from Federal to State Ownership and Operation [Olson as Expert Witness], 1982-1984 (Box-folder 4/1)
        - Alaska Railroad Transfer Advisory Commission Interim Report, 1983 (Box-folder 4/2)
        - Twentieth Century Race Riots Presentation [Assitant Professor at Indiana University], 1972-1974 (Box-folder 4/3)
        - Expert Witness Before the Atomic Safety and Licensing Board of the United States of America Nuclear Regulation Commission in the Matter of the Long Island Lighting Company's Soreham Nuclear Power Station, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 4/4)
        - Shoreham Nuclear Plant, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 4/5)
        - Business card file, 1936-1983 (Box-folder 4/6)
        - Proposed Emergency Planning Contentions Modified to Reflect Revision 3 of the LILCO Plan, 1984 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Labor Research and Community Outreach, Subseries E
      - Labor Bibliography, Part 1
        - Labor Bibliography, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Speeches: State Convention; AFL/CIO, ILWU 29th International Convention, Bridges Bust Ceremony, SPEEA Conference, Part 2
        - Speeches on Labor and the International Longshore and Warehouse Union, 1992-2000 (Box-folder 4/9)
        - Speeches on Labor and the International Longshore and Warehouse Union, 1998-2000 (Box-folder 4/10)
      - Books About Labor, Part 3
        - Goldblatt, Louis, and Otto Hagel. 1963. Men and machines; a photo story of the mechanization and modernization agreement between the International Longshoremen's & Warehousemen's Union and the Pacific Maritime Association now in operation in the ports of (Box-folder 4/11)
        - Pierce County Labor Centennial Committee (Pierce County, Wash.). 1989. To live in dignity: Pierce County labor, 1883-1989. Tacoma, Wash: The Committee. (Box-folder 4/12)
        - DeLeon, Richard Edward. 1992. Left coast city: progressive politics in San Francisco, 1975-1991. Lawrence, Kan: University Press of Kansas. (Box-folder 4/13)
        - Seattle. 1971. The Seattle general strike: an account of what happened in Seattle, and especially in the Seattle Labor Movement during the general strike, February 6 to 11, 1919. Seattle, Wash: Shorey Book Store. (Box-folder 4/14)
      - Research Notes on Seattle Unions, Part 4
        - [Seattle Union Notes], 1971-2007 (Box-folder 4/15)
        - Boeing Workers Strike, 1994-2004 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Research and Consultation on Port of Seattle and Seattle Waterfront Workers, Subseries F
      - Port of Seattle History and Studies, Part 1
        - Port Study [with Professor Michael Denning of Indiana University], 1988-2002 (Box-folder 4/17)
        - Early History of the Port of Seattle [Struggle for Public Ownership by Padraic Burke], 1977 (Box-folder 4/18)
        - Port of Seattle: Properties of the Port: 1915,1916,1917, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 5/1)
        - Port of Seattle: Bell Street Terminal, 1915 (Box-folder 5/2)
        - Port of Seattle: Containerization of Waterborne Commerce [Reports and Research], 1965-1968 (Box-folder 5/3)
        - Port of Seattle History [Planning and Industrial Development], 1915-1968 (Box-folder 5/4)
        - Port of Seattle: Annual Report [1915, "Farmers Day"] (Box-folder 5/5)
        - Port of Seattle: Annual Report [1919] (Box-folder 5/6)
        - Microfilm Images [Union Images, etc.], c. 1930s (Box-folder 5/7)
      - Research on Waterfront Strikes, Part 2
        - The San Francisco Maritime and General Strikes of 1934: A Rank-and-File Movement for Social and Economic Independence [Essay by Anne Alexandra Mini], 1988 (Box-folder 5/8)
        - Labor History [American Labor, Seattle General Strike of 1919, The History of Mayday, A Brief History of U.S Asian Labor, Work on the Waterfront], 1992-2007 (Box-folder 5/9)
        - 1921 Strike - Seattle Daily Union Record, c. 1921 (Box-folder 5/10)
        - 1934 Strike - Miscellaneous, c. 1934 (Box-folder 5/11)
        - 1921 Strike: Miscellaneous (Box-folder 5/12)
        - 1920-1929 [Port of Seattle Correspondence: Kitchen Cabinet], c. 1911-1995 (Box-folder 5/13)
        - 1948 Strike - The Dispatcher (Box-folder 5/14)
        - 1971-1972 Strike - Port of Seattle Material, etc., 1971-1973 (Box-folder 5/15)
        - 1971-1972 Strike - The Dispatcher (Box-folder 5/16)
        - 1971-1972 Strike - Merle Adlum Papers [Marine Terminals Department Activity Reports July 1971- January 1972] (Box-folder 5/17)
        - 1971-1972 Strike - Merle Adlum Papers [Port Lines and Attached Material August 12, 1971 - February 22, 1972] (Box-folder 5/18)
        - 1934 Stirke - Fadden Papers (Box-folder 5/19)
      - Port Papers and Correspondence, Part 3
        - Paine vs. Port of Seattle, c. 1911-1912 (Box-folder 5/20)
        - [Interdepartmental Correspondence: University of Washington], 1981 (Box-folder 5/21)
        - Kerr: The Progressives of Washington [Articles], 1910-1912 (Box-folder 5/22)
        - 1950-1959, 1957 (Box-folder 5/23)
        - 1970-1979 [Port of Seattle Plans and Elections], 1977 (Box-folder 5/24)
        - 1960-1969 [Council Advocates Pamplet], 1980-1981 (Box-folder 5/25)
      - Harbor Island Episode Manuscript: Chittenden’s Personal Account, Part 4
        - Chittenden, Hiram Martin. 1915. The Harbor Island episode, a history., c. 1915 (Box-folder 5/26)
      - International Longshore and Warehouse Union Contract Documents, Part 5
        - Pacific Coast Longshore Contract Document [Contains Personal Inscription], 1990-1993 (Box-folder 5/27)
        - Pacific Coast Longshore Contract Document [Contains Personal Inscription], 1993-1996 (Box-folder 5/28)
      - International Longshore and Warehouse Union, Part 6
        - Maximum Loads for Standard Commodities; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 5/29)
        - Revival: The Longshore Strike and the Rise of Industrial Unionism, 1934 (Box-folder 5/30)
        - International Longshore and Warehouse Union, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 5/31)
        - International Longshore and Warehouse Union: Affiliations/Disaffiliation [Research: Solidarity and Democracy], 1937-2004 (Box-folder 5/32)
        - International Longshore and Warehouse Union: Fight for Hiring Hall [Copies of newspapers], 1948-1950 (Box-folder 5/33)
        - International Longshore and Warehouse Union [Union Busting, Los Angeles Daily News, Application Affliations, Solidarity and Democracy by Nowell Bamberger], 1937-1992 (Box-folder 5/34)
        - International Longshore and Warehouse Union [Affliations with AFL- CIO, WFTU], 2003-2004 (Box-folder 5/35)
        - Dave Beck, 1993-2004 (Box-folder 5/36)
    - Research and Consultation on Blanket Primaries, Subseries G
      - Washington Open Primary, Part 1
        - Washington Open Primary, 2001-2005 (Box-folder 6/1)
        - Washington Open Primary [Email, Press Clippings on Washington Blanket Primary/Open Primary Presentation to Council of State Governments], 2000-2005 (Box-folder 6/2)
      - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed, Part 2
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Olson as Consultant in Blanket Primary Case], 1990-2002 (Box-folder 6/3)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Olson as Consultant in Blanket Primary Case], 2002 (Box-folder 6/4)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Olson as Consultant in Blanket Primary Case: Deposition, 2001 (Box-folder 6/5)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Olson as Consultant in Blanket Primary Case: Deposition, Newspaper Clippings, Payment], 2001-2002 (Box-folder 6/6)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Olson Declaration and Defense Responses], 2001 (Box-folder 6/7)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Support/Opposition for Summary Judgement], 2001 (Box-folder 6/8)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Support/Opposition for Summary Judgement], 2001 (Box-folder 6/9)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Report on the Consequences of Blanket Primary, Olson Statement], 2001 (Box-folder 6/10)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Deposition Examinations and Rules for Precinct Caucuses], 2000-2001 (Box-folder 6/11)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Additional Court Documents, Correspondence with Jeff Evans (ADA), Olson's Curriculum Vitae, 2001 (Box-folder 6/12)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Expert Witness Disclosures, California State Open Primary Court Document, Mark A Smith (Assitant Professor) Paper], 1999-2001 (Box-folder 6/13)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Expert Witness Testimonies, Rules for Precinct Caucuses (1996,1998,2000), Proposed Bylaws Changes], 1996-2001 (Box-folder 6/14)
        - Washington State Democratic Party vs. Sam Reed [Rublican Committe of Washington, Intervenors' Responses, Comparison of Political Party Performance, Jordan Triplett Paper, 2001 (Box-folder 6/15)
      - Voting at the Political Party Fault Line Manuscript, Part 3
        - Voting at the Political Party Fault Line [Sprial Bound Manuscript by Bruce E. Cain, Elisabeth R. Gerber], 2002 (Box-folder 6/16)
      - California and Washington State Primary, Part 4
        - California Blanket Primary and Washington Blanket Primary, 1999-2008 (Box-folder 6/17)
        - California Blanket Primary and Washington Blanket Primary [Newspaper Clippings and Grange Information], 2000-2001 (Box-folder 6/18)
      - California Blanket Primary, Part 5
        - California Blanket Primary [Olson as Expert Witness Statement, California State Democratic Party vs. Bill Jones], 1997-1998 (Box-folder 6/19)
        - California Blanket Primary [Olson as Expert Witness, California Democratic Party vs. Bill Jones (Trial Documents), Olson Curriculum Vitae, University Reporters], 1996-1997 (Box-folder 6/20)
        - California Blanket Primary [Olson as Expert Witness: Correspondence with Kyungah Suk, Trial Brief, Federal Reporter, Newspaper Articles], 1997 (Box-folder 7/1)
        - California Blanket Primary [Olson as Expert Witness: Correspondence with Kyungah Suk, Newspaper Articles], 1997-1998 (Box-folder 7/2)
        - California Blanket Primary [Olson as Expert Witness: Revised Statements, Payment Agreements, Defendants' Jonit Trial Brief (Post Trial Brief), 1997-1998 (Box-folder 7/3)
        - California Blanket Primary [Olson as Expert Witness: Correspondence with Kyungah Suk, Newspaper Clippings, California Democratic Party vs. Bill Jones Trial Transcript, Defendants' Joint Reply Brief], 1997 (Box-folder 7/4)
      - California Democratic Party vs. Bill Jones, Part 6
        - California Democratic Party vs. Bill Jones [Deposition of David Olson], 1997 (Box-folder 7/5)
- David Olson papers, 1937-2006; 1994-2006; 5672-002; 2.57 cubic feet 3 boxes
  Research materials and publications on Olson's research specialties of labor unions and port studies, particularly the International Longshoremen's Association and its West Coast successor, the International Longshore and Warehouse Union.
  No restrictions on access.
  Donated by Sandra Olson